Guide to the Van Ness-Philip Family Papers 1711-1963 (bulk 1711-1945) MS 653
New-York Historical Society
Van Ness-Philip Family Papers
1711-1963 (bulk 1711-1945)
New-York Historical Society
MS 653
39 Linear feet (91 boxes)
The collection documents the Van Ness, Philip and Worthington families from the late 1700's to the early 1900's. The collection consists of correspondence, journals, maps, printed matter, genealogical material, etc, of the Van Ness-Philip Family. Names of note include: General John P. Van Ness, William Henry Philip, wife Eliza Worthington Philip and sons John Van Ness Philip and Herman Hoffman Philip. Included in the collection are also general files of the Van Ness, Philip and Worthington families relating to social, political and business matters.
Provenance
Purchase, 1980.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Historical Note
The Van Ness-Philip Family Papers reflect a century of these two connected New York State families' participation in public, commercial, social and military life from the late 1700's to early 1900's.
The collection begins with David Burnes, an original proprietor of land in downtown Washington, D.C. and father-in-law to General John P. Van Ness. John P. Van Ness's involvement in politics, business, banking, the War of 1812, the election of 1828 make him a important figure in the public forum and his many correspondents include Gilbert Stuart, Andrew Jackson, Aaron Burr, John Quincy Adams, John Jacob Astor and Daniel Webster. The Van Ness family papers also include information of Ann E., Cornelius P., James, Marcia, Peter William P. and William W. Van Ness. These papers also document the family carpet business, variously called James Philip and Son, and W.G. Philip and Company.
Military history is also documented in the collection of John Van Ness Philip (d. 1862), an officer who served in both the Mexican and Civil Wars. He took part in the Kossuth mission aboard the U.S.S. Mississippi in 1851 and the invasion of California in 1846 aboard the U.S.S. Cyane in the Mexican American War.
A large part of the collection focuses on the family of William Henry Philip (ca.1840's-1881), who attended Lenox Academy and Williams College, served in the Civil War, ran for Congress and worked as a lawyer and businessman in Washington, D.C. He married Eliza Worthington Philip (ca.1860's-1896) in 1864 and they had two sons, John Van Ness Philip and Howard Hoffman Philip. The family settled at Talavera in Claverack, Columbia County, New York, and later lived in Washington, D.C. and Europe. John Van Ness Philip attended Princeton, served in the Spanish-American War, was a lawyer and social figure in Washington, D.C. and involved in Columbia County politics. Herman Hoffman Philip, (ca.1870's-1950) attended Cambridge University, traveled in the far West, served with the Rough Riders on San Juan Hill and provided diplomatic service in the Mid-East, Africa, Scandinavia, and South America.
The Worthington family papers include those of Midshipman Thomas B. Worthington and his physician father Charles Worthington, lawyer William M. Worthington John G. Worthington and his early law practice in Cincinnati, Ohio, and later years in Washington, D.C. as well as additional family correspondence.
Genealogical information of the Van Ness family, as well as clippings and mausoleum information, such as the deed and cemetery plot are located at the end of the collection along with genealogical files of the Philip and Worthington families.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains more than 15,000 letters and documents of the Van Ness-Philips family from the late 1700's to the early 1900's. The oldest part of the collection focuses on General John P. Van Ness, son of Peter Van Ness, a congressman from New York and later the mayor of Washington D.C. There is also much political correspondence between John P. Van Ness and Martin Van Buren, James Roosevelt and others concerning New York State affairs. Included in the series are some 30 signatures of autographic value, besides Van Buren and Roosevelt, among them: John Quincy Adams, Andrew Jackson, John Jacob Astor, Daniel Webster, Francis Scott Key, James Monroe, Nicholas Biddle, Albert Gallatin, Zebulon Pike, Benjamin Latrobe and Gilbert Stuart. Series I contains the Washington plat books, surveys and correspondence of his father-in-law, David Burnes.
Miltary documents, correspondence and diaries of Officer John Van Ness Philip (d. 1862) who served in both the Mexican and Civil Wars are of signicant importance concerning the Kossuth mission aboard the U.S.S. Mississippi in 1851 and the invasion of California in 1846 aboard the U.S.S. Cyane in the Mexican American War.
The collection also contains personal papers detailing the education of William Henry Philip at Lenox Academy and Williams College and his travels in Europe. There are also papers of military and political value regarding his service in the Civil War, candidacy for Congress, and life as a lawyer and businessman in Washington, D.C. Included in the collection are the personal papers and correspondence of his wife, Eliza Worthington Philip and their two sons, John Van Ness Philip and Herman Hoffman Philip, who were both active in business and politics.
The Philip Family Papers contains letters of Theodore Roosevelt, as well as letters of Franklin D. and Eleanor Roosevelt. Also included are writings, speeches, illustrations and volumes.
Material relating to the Worthington family, ca. 1817-1900, includes correspondence, 1817-21, between Midshipman Thomas B. Worthington and his physician father Charles Worthington; correspondence and papers of lawyer William M. Worthington; correspondence, ca. 1830's-1875, of John G. Worthington, covering his early law practice in Cincinnati, Ohio, and later years in Washington, D.C.; and family correspondence, ca. 1850's-1900.
Items of note also include one folder of oversize material containing commissions of Herman Hoffman Philip, that are signed by Presidents T. Roosevelt, Taft, Harding, Coolidge, Hover, F.D. Roosevelt. There are also some commissions of John Van Ness Philip (d. 1949) signed by President McKinley.
Arrangement
The Van Ness-Philip Papers are arranged in the following eleven series:
Missing Title
Series I. James and David Burnes
Series II. John P. Van Ness
Series III. Van Ness Family
Series IV. John Van Ness Philip (d. 1862)
Series V. William Henry Philip
Series VI. Eliza W. Philip
Series VII. John Van Ness Philip (d. 1949)
Series VIII. Herman Hoffman Philip
Series IX. Philip Family
Series X. Worthington Family
Series XI. Oversize Materials
Series XII. Genealogy
Genealogies (histories); Commissions (orders for works).; Account books.; Americans -- Foreign countries.; Carpets; Diplomatic and consular service; Mexican War, 1846-1848; Spanish-American War, 1898; Diaries.; California; Deeds.; Cincinnati (Ohio); Claverack (N.Y.); Columbia County (N.Y.); New York (State); Washington (D.C.).; United States -- History -- War of 1812.; Lawyers; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Logbooks.; Kossuth, Lajos, 1802-1894; Lenox Academy; Philip, Catharine Douw, 1797-1866; Philip, Eliza Worthington, 1842-1896; Philip, Elizabeth Worthington, 1876-; Philip, Gaston Pearson, 1874-; Philip, Henry G., 1793-1829; Philip, Herman Hoffman, 1872-1951; Philip, John Van Ness, 1823-1862; Philip, John Van Ness, 1866-1949; Philip, Martin Hoffman, 1826-1888; Philip, William Henry, 1824-1881; Phillips family; Princeton University; University of Cambridge; Van Ness, Cornelius P. (Cornelius Peter), 1782-1852; Van Ness, John Peter, 1770-1846; Van Ness, Marcia, -1832; Van Ness, William Peter, 1778-1826; Van Ness, William W., 1776-1823; Williams College; Worthington family; Worthington, Charles, 1759-1836; Worthington, Elizabeth Phillips, 1809-1889; Worthington, John G., 1798-1875; Worthington, Thomas B., -1822; Worthington, William M.; Burnes, David; Burns family
- Series I: James and David Burnes
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes correspondence and papers of James and David Burnes. The materials consist mostly of land deeds and property business. David Burnes was an original proprietor of land in downtown Washington, D.C. and father-in-law to John P. Van Ness.
  - Burnes: deeds wills, undated, 1792-1807 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Burnes, James & David deeds, 1752-1800 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Burnes, James & David deeds, 1752-1800 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Will of Thomas Fletchall, planter, 1783 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Land papers, 1723-1782 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Indentures, bonds, business correspondence, 1743-1783 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Land papers, 1711-1796 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Accounts, papers, notes, circa 1780-1790 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bills, notes, business correspondence, 1794-1801 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - David Burnes: letters, 1790-1793 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lands commissioners & their proprietors, taxes, undated, 1769-1796 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lands commissioners & their proprietors, taxes, 1797-1826 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters of John Oakley, undated, 1799-1800 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fragment of a deed, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Account of property David Burnes, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Re: David Burnes estate, misc., 1774-1803, undated, 1719-1780 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series II: John P. Van Ness
  Series II is dedicated to General John Peter Van Ness, David Burne's son-in-law. Series includes correspondence and papers, ca. 1788-1845 concerning subjects such as politics, business, banking, the War of 1812, election of 1828, the Van Ness mansion and mausoleum, land dealings, and Washington social life.
  - Misc. letters (John P. Van Ness, Mrs. Van Ness), music, undated, 1802-1851 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Re: portraits of John P. and Mrs. John P., undated, 1805-1833 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with B. H. Latrobe, architect for building Van Ness mansion, 1811-1815 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with B. H. Latrobe, architect for building Van Ness mansion, 1816-1820 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Misc. correspondence, 1802-1830 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Misc. correspondence, 1831-1848 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence re: politics & law, 1803-1827 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence re: politics & law, 1829-1841 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Re: Militia (NY & Washington?) as Major, Colonel, Brig-Gen., General, 1802-1811 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Speeches, petition for impeachment of A. Burr, undated, 1804 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The case of Samuel Hawkins, 1818-1825 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letters, misc., 1802-1845 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Controversy around John P. Van Ness' "official" greeting & President James Monroe, 1817 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Papers re: sale of property bet. John P. Van Ness & John Quincy Adams, 1815-1821 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Letters: Van Buren, Monroe, 1802-1844 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bond, letters John Jacob Astor, 1809 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Letters: Daniel Webster, speech, 1836-1851 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sale of Van Alen farm in Kinderhook, 1809 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Papers re: guardianship of the children of James Burns, 1805-1810 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence re: Isaac Clason Estate, undated, 1813-1819 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Re: Laight Case, undated, 1805-1816 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Re: attack on Washington D.C. by British, 1814 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Woodward Affair, undated, 1804-1809 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Memorandum re: intrigue among Clay, Adams, Webster re: Election 1828 & Jackson, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Commissions (legal, military), 1788-1813 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Misc. letters, receipts, undated, 1793-1845 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Settlement of estate #1, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Settlement of estate #2, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Settlement of estate #3, 1848-1852 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Business correspondence - bills and receipts, undated, 1804-1810 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Business correspondence - bills and receipts, 1810-1842 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Business correspondence - land acquisition and rental agreements, 1810-1832 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Re: William Duncanson, undated, 1802-1805 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Business correspondence, undated, 1804-1845 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Re: account with D. Clagett, Clagett & Washington, 1819-1831 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Bills, receipts, legal matters with John Weightman, John Knapp, David Brent, etc., 1804-1812 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Business with Stoughton Gannt, Charles Varden, others, 1802-1841 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Re: sloop "industry", 1803-1814 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Misc. business, undated, 1800-1815 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Misc. business, 1817-1845 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Washington, D.C. business correspondence, 1795-1827 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Washington, D.C. business correspondence, 1828-1845 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence from Richmond, VA, 1823-1843 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Re: silk manufacture, 1844-1845 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Business correspondence, undated, 1812-1846 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Business correspondence with [W. E.] Boyd, 1813-1819 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Business correspondence with J. H. Barney, 1803-1810 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Re: Elizabeth Bacon, undated, 1839-1845 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Re: D. G. Orme, 1837-1842 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Re: Richard Cutts, 1807-1818 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Misc. business papers, undated, 1800-1847 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Promissory notes and receipts, 1806-1814 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Notes, checks, etc., 1803-1814 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Business letters, undated, 1802-1842 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Misc. business correspondence, 1808-1844 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Loose account books, circa 1700-1900 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - John P. Van Ness vs Brohawn & Byus, 1803-1837 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - The Washington Theatre - building & maintenance, 1803-1840 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Washington, D.C: incorporation/autonomy question, undated, 1803-[1805] (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Washington Dancing Assembly, 1805 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Bank of U.S. (#1), undated, 1806-1809 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Re: Bank of U.S. (#2), undated, 1810-1838 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Van Ness Mauseleum, Washington, D.C., undated, 1814-1842 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Kennedy claims re: C & O Canal, 1823-1837 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Re: Chesapeake & Canal, newspaper clippings, 1833-1834, 1984-1986 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Bank of Metropolis - accounts and memos, letters (M. L. Davis), undated, 1814-1841 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Central Cholera Hospital, Washington, D.C., 1832 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Western Cholera Hospital, Washington, D.C., 1832 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Eastern Cholera Hospital, Washington, D.C., 1832 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Receipts and bills of Washington tradesmen (#1), undated, 1803-1819 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Receipts and bills of Washington tradesmen (#2), 1820-1829 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Receipts and bills of Washington tradesmen (#3), 1830s-1844 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Domestic receipts (1), undated, 1803-1819 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Domestic receipts (2), 1820-1829 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Domestic receipts (3), 1830-1839 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Domestic receipts (4), 1840-1842 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Re: Peres Packard, 1819-1829 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Receipts and bills (1), undated, 1800's-1819 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Receipts and bills (2), 1820-1829 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Receipts and bills (3), 1830's-1847 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Misc. business, notes (#1), letters, deeds, undated, [1800-1819] (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Misc. business, notes (#2), letters, deeds, [1820-1830] (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Misc. business, notes (#3), letters, deeds, [1830-1850] (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Misc. receipts and notes, 1803-1845 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Receipts and notes (E1), 1815-1840 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Receipts and bills (F1), 1800-1845 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Receipts and bills (F2), 1800-1844 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Receipts and bills (F3), 1800-1844 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Receipts and bills (F4), 1800-1844 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Receipts and bills (G1), undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Receipts and bills (G2), undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Receipts and bills (H1), 1800-1845 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Receipts and bills (H2), 1800-1845 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Receipts and bills (H3), undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Receipts and bills (I1), 1790-undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Receipts and bills (I2), 1790-1830 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Receipts and bills (I3), 1790-1830 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Receipts and bills (J1), undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Receipts and bills (J2), undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Receipts and bills (J3), undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Receipts and bills (K1), undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Receipts and bills (K2), undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Receipts and bills (K3), undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Receipts and bills (L1), undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Receipts and bills (L2), undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Receipts and bills (L3), undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Receipts and bills (M1), undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Receipts and bills (M2), undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Receipts and bills (N1), undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Receipts and bills (N2), undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Receipts and bills, 1800-1840 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Receipts and bills, household business, money transactions, 1802-1845 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Bills received, 1802-1818 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Receipts, business correspondence, 1793-1844 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Receipts, business correspondence, 1800-1844 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Household businees, personal business, misc. (1), undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Household businees, personal business, misc. (2), undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Farm land, management, sale correspondences, notes, accounts, land in Westmoreland county, 1788-1824 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Legal financial papers, circa 1790-1816 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Land claims, 1791-1830 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Papers re: Glebe property #1, circa 1700-1800 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Re: Glebe property (#2), circa 1790-1835 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - John P. Van Ness vs Rientzel (Daniel), 1803-1808 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - John P. Van Ness and William Brent, U.K., legal fees, 1816-1832 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Misc. D.C. property, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Business: leases, deeds, correspondence, 1816-1834 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Walter Jones case with the Bank of Metropolis, 1817-1826 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Widow Conner suit, circa 1847 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Leases and deeds, 1810-1843 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Leases, deeds, agreements, 1805-1845 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Leases and accounts of extended family, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Deeds, leases, notes, accounts, business letters (1), 1803-1844 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Deeds, leases, notes, accounts, business letters (2), 1803-1844 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Cases, leases, accounts, 1819-1830 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Leases, deeds, agreements, D.C. property and taxes, accounts of extended family (1), 1800-1848 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Leases, deeds, agreements, D.C. property and taxes, accounts of extended family (2), 1800-1848 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Leases, deeds, agreements, D.C. property and taxes, accounts of extended family (3), undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Bank of Metropolis - John P. Van Ness assigned mortgage, land and property assignment, circa 1840-1850 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Judgements, etc., 1828-1841 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Deeds, memos, lease, 1800-1845 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Leases, deeds, agreements, 1800-1845 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Leases, deeds, agreements, etc., 1800-1845 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Leases, deeds, agreements, etc., 1800-1845 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Leases, deeds, agreements, etc., 1800-1845 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Leases, deeds, agreements, etc., 1800-1845 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Original plats and maps of Washington, D.C., circa 1796 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Original plats and maps of Washington, D.C., circa 1975 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Deeds, memorandums, 1804-1845 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Deeds, leases, agreements, 1818-1845 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Leases, deeds, agreements, undated, 1822-1845 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Indentures, 1816-1844 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Indentures, 1815-1844 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Indentures, deeds, 1804-1846 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Dinner, 1812 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Series III: Van Ness Family
  The Van Ness Family series includes correspondence and papers of Henry G. and Catharine Douw Philip as well as correspondence, papers, and account books of the family carpet business, variously called James Philip and Son, and W.G. Philip and Company.
  - Letters: Gertrude Hoffman, Catherine Van Alen; Family history, history of Talavera, undated, 1804-1848 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Education of Ann E. Van Ness, 1815-1819 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Letters from William P. Van Ness to John P. Van Ness, 1802-1827 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Estate of William W. Van Ness, Debts owed and by John P. Van Ness, 1823-1825 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Letters from James Van Ness, Defalcation; about George and John P. Van Ness, Letter from Cornelia (niece), 1830-1839 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Cornelius Peter Van Ness wit John P. Van Ness (brother), 1820-1847 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Peter Van Ness (d. 1804), and son: letters, 1763-1804 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Funeral book: Marcia Van Ness (1832), letters, indenture, undated, 1832-1844 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Letters: Cornelius P. Van Ness, undated, 1831-1852 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Letters of Arthur Middleton, letter G. Ousley, 1829-1843 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence of James J. Roosevelt, some re: George Van Ness affair, 1832-1836 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Letter - William Worthington to John P. Van Ness, misc. from other Van Ness family, 1808-1864 (Box 15, Folder 12)
- Series IV: John Van Ness Philip (d. 1862)
  This series contains correspondence (dated 1837-62), diaries, and naval log book of the officer, who served in both the Mexican and Civil Wars. There is detailed information concerning the Kossuth mission aboard the U.S.S. Mississippi in 1851 and the invasion of California in 1846 aboard the U.S.S. Cyane in the Mexican American War.
  - Correspondence to William Hears and to John Van Ness Philip, circa 1830-1840 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to John Van Ness Philip, 1837 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - School papers, 1837-1839 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1838 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and diploma from Rensselaer Institute, 1839 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1841 Jan.-1841 Jul. (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1841 Aug.-1841 Dec. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1842 Jan.-1842 Jun. (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1842 Aug.-1842 Dec. (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1843 Jan.-1843 Apr. (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Commission as midshipman signed by President Tyler, 1843 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1843May-1843 Aug. (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1843 Sep.-1843 Dec. (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1844 Jan.-1844 Apr. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: "Visa" and Rome, 1844 May-1844 Dec. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1845 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, proclamation to the inhabitants of California, list of cargo (2), 1846 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: general orders, 1847 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, exams in U.S. Naval School, 1848 Jan.-1848 Aug. (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1848 Sep.-1848 Dec. (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, undated, circa 1840 Jan.-1850 May (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, circa 1840 Jun.-1850 Aug. (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, circa 1840 Sep.-1850 Dec. (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1849 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1850-1851 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1852 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1853 (Box 18, Folder 7)